Preliminary guide to the Gordon Murray papers, 1811-1971 MS2179
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gordon Murray papers
1811-1971
1966-1971
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Murray, Gordon M.
MS2179
2.75 Linear Feet 6 document boxes
This collection contains the working files of Gordon Murray during his time with the Department of Transportation. These materials date from 1811-1971 with the bulk of the records falling between 1966-1971. The files are composed of correspondence, memos, and briefings all related to aspects of transportation from aeronautics, maritime, commerce transportation, railroad, and urban transportation.
Biographical note
Gordon M. Murray (d. April 8, 1991) worked in various capacities with the Federal government for more than 35 years. Murray worked for the Works Progress Administration and later served as an economist for the Federal Housing Administration and Associate Chief Economist for the Public Housing Administration. In his capacity of Assistant Division Chief for Transportation in the Bureau of the Budget, Murray helped draft both the President's Transportation Message of 1962 and the Urban Mass Transportation Act of 1964. This is the act that created the Department of Transportation. Murray joined the Department of Transportation in 1967 and served as the special assistant to the Department of Transportation's first secretary, Alan Boyd, and later as assistant administrator of the Urban Mass Transportation Administration.
By 1972, Murray had retired. In retirement he spent twelve years as a consultant to the World Bank's Economic Development Institute.
Murray was born in New Jersey and a graduate of Cornell University. His wife, Gloria Ann Grainger Murray died in 1975.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gordon Murray, 1983.
Arrangement
Original organization retained and is primarily chronological.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the chronological files and other working papers of Gordon Murray. These materials date from 1811-1971 with the bulk of the records falling between 1966-1971. The chronological files are composed of correspondence, memos, and briefings all related to aspects of transportation from aeronautics, maritime, commerce transportation, railroad, and urban transportation. There are also files related to highway safety and regulation. There are working files that Murray had related to the work of the Department of Transportation and specifically the legislation that formed the Department of Transportation. There are also files related to the history of transportation in the United States and public laws associated with transportation.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Transportation; Railroads; Urban transportation; Express highways; Aeronautics; Department of Transportation
- Chron. file -- 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Chron. file -- 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Chron. file -- 1960 [1/2] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Chron. file -- 1960 [2/2] (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Chron. file -- 1961 [1/3] (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Chron. file -- 1961 [2/3] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chron. file -- 1961 [3/3] (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Chron. file -- 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Chron. file -- 1963 [1/2] (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Chron. file -- 1963 [2/2] (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Chron. file -- 1964 [1/2] (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Chron. file -- 1964 [2/2] (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Chron. file -- 1965 [1/2] (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Chron. file -- 1965 [2/2] (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Chron. file -- 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Chron. file -- 1967 (folder 1) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Chron. file -- 1967 (folder 2) [1/2] (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Chron. file -- 1967 (folder 2) [2/2] (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Chron. file -- 1968 [1/2] (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Chron. file -- 1968 [2/2] (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Chron. file -- 1969 [1/2] (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Chron. file -- 1969 [2/2] (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Chron. file -- 1969-1971 [1/2] (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Chron. file -- 1969-1971 [2/2] (Box 3, Folder 6)
- A program of legislative and administrative proposals for Transportation Regulation [1/2], 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- A program of legislative and administrative proposals for Transportation Regulation [2/2], 1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Regulatory standards in common ownerships in transportation, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Dept. of Transportation Briefing book, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Although this folder and the following folder have different titles they appear to be from the same briefing book.
- DOT Briefing Book: Reasons for bringing together in DOT all safety functions, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Although this folder and the preceding folder have different titles they appear to be from the same briefing book.
- Dept. of Transportation Organization Task Force [1/3], 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Dept. of Transportation Organization Task Force [2/3], 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Dept. of Transportation Organization Task Force [3/3], 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Legislative History of the DOT Act [1/3], 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Legislative History of the DOT Act [2/3], 1967 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Legislative History of the DOT Act [3/3], 1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Messages to Congress by US presidents dealing with surface transportation, 1811-1964 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- History of the U.S. Maritime Service vol 1., 1943 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Public Laws 85th-86th Congress, 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Public Laws 87th-88th Congress, 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Public Laws 89th Congress, 1965-1970 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Public Laws 90th-91st Congress, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Presidential Messages Johnson Book II, 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 3)